<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The intentions of the armie of the kingdome of Scotland, declared to their bretheren of England: by the Commissioners of the late Parliament, and by the generall, noblemen, barrons, and other officers of the armie.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21921.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110876</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">44920423</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 44920423</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173870</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00666)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173870)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1362:7 or 2104:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The intentions of the armie of the kingdome of Scotland, declared to their bretheren of England: by the Commissioners of the late Parliament, and by the generall, noblemen, barrons, and other officers of the armie.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
                  <author>Henderson, Alexander, 1583?-1646.</author>
                  <author>Scotland. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Jan Evertsz Cloppenburg],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Yeare of God, 1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and publisher from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Alexander Henderson.</note>
                  <note>Title vignette: printer's mark.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴, B³.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, edges torn, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1362:7 as STC 21921.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of original in: Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Pamphlets.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173870:1"/>
            <p>THE INTENTIONS OF THE ARMIE OF THE KINDOME OF SCOTLAND, <hi>DECLARED</hi> TO THEIR BRETHREN OF ENGLAND:</p>
            <p>BY <hi>THE COMMISSIONERS OF THE LATE Parliament, and by the Generall, Noblemen, Barrons, and other Officers of the Armie.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <p>EN LAET HET BOECA DESER WET VAN VWEN MONDE NIET COMEN <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſu. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare of God. 1640.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:173870:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173870:2"/>
            <head>THE INTENTIONS OF THE ARMIE OF THE KINGDOME OF SCOTLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE beſt indeavours and greateſt works wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the good hand and <hi>providence</hi> of <hi>God</hi> have been moſt evident and ſenſible, and the hearts and intentions of men, called to be the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, moſt <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>ſincere,</hi> Though they found approbation with the <hi>wiſer ſort,</hi> and ſuch as are given to <hi>obſervation,</hi> yet they have ever been ſubject to be miſconſtrued by blind <hi>ſuſpition,</hi> to be reproved by cavelling cenſure, which maketh place for it ſelfe to enter where it findeth none, and to be condemned of the <hi>ignorant,</hi> but moſt of all of the <hi>malicious,</hi> who cannot be pleaſed even when <hi>God</hi> is beſt pleaſed; and when men ſeek to approve themſelves to every ones Conſcience, but in their hearts wiſh rather that the Temple ſhould not be built, Religion never reformed, and they themſelves <hi>Iſſachar</hi> like, couch betweene the two burthens, then that they ſhould be in their wordly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects or poſſeſſions oppoſed or troubled. The <hi>deliverance</hi> of the people of <hi>God</hi> of old from the Aegyptian <hi>ſervitude;</hi> The <hi>redemption</hi> of the Kirk by the Son of <hi>God,</hi> and the planting of Chriſtian Religion by his <hi>ſervants,</hi> and the vindication of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion from Romiſh Superſtition and Tyranny, which are the Greateſt and moſt <hi>wonderfull works</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> have been moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly calumniated, and ſpitefullly ſpurned againſt by the <hi>wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The nature and quality of this <hi>good worke</hi> wherin the <hi>Lord</hi> hath honoured us to be <hi>actors,</hi> and the experience which we have found of continuall oppoſition ſince the beginning may teach us, if we be not <hi>as the Horſe and Mule which have no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> that we are to expect the gainſaying of <hi>ſinners,</hi> and that nothing can be hatched in hell by Satan, or prompted by his Suppoſts, on earth, which will not be produced to make us and the Cauſe of <hi>God</hi> which we maintain odious to all men, but moſt of all to our Neighbours and deareſt Brethren. When we ſhall now enter into <hi>England</hi> it will be layed to our charge that we mind nothing but Invaſion, and that no leſſe hath been
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:173870:3"/>intended by us from the beginning then under the pretext of ſeeeking our Religion and Liberties to enrich our ſelves with their <hi>poſſeſſions</hi> and <hi>goods:</hi> But our peaceable cariage many years paſt before the time of thoſe late <hi>troubles,</hi> our <hi>Informations, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrances</hi> publiſhed to the world, wherin we have Curſed all Nationall Invaſion, and our willingneſſe when we were in Armes to lay them down upon the ſmall hopes of injoying our Religion and Liberties; and our forbearing now, by way of repriſall, to ſatisfie our ſelves upon the Shippes and goods of our deare Brethren of <hi>England,</hi> for thoſe Ships and goods of ours, that have been taken by the Kings Ships, which poſſibly we might have been able to doe, had not Juſtice for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden us, to take from them, whom we are aſſured, neither wiſh us <hi>harme,</hi> nor have done us <hi>wrong,</hi> will be conceived by the <hi>wiſe</hi> and well affected to be more plain and ſure evidences of our meaning then all that <hi>malice</hi> can deviſe, or <hi>calumnie</hi> can expreſſe againſt us.</p>
            <p>Neither have any new emergents adhered, but rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed our former <hi>reſolutions:</hi> for although both before and ſince the Late Pacification we have been highly injured by ſome Papiſts and Prelats, and their adherents there, who have been, and are ſtill ſeeking no leſſe, then that we ſhould no more be a Kirk or Nation, and therfore themſelves cannot thinke but we muſt accompt of them as <hi>Gods</hi> enemies and ours: Yet above all the <hi>favours</hi> we have received from the good people and body of the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> One there is which hath highly honoured them before the world, and endeared them unto us more then before, which ſhall never be forgotten by us, and we hope ſhall be thankfully remembred by our Children, and Childrens Children after us to all <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations;</hi> That when upon miſinformation the Councell of <hi>England</hi> had concluded to raiſe Force againſt us, when the Parliament of <hi>Ireland</hi> had offered their Perſons and Eſtates for ſupply againſt us; when all <hi>plots</hi> and <hi>policies</hi> were ſet on worke, and Publick <hi>Declarations</hi> by Authority were made, and the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> called for this very end, when we had been traduced, and Proclaimed as Traytors and Rebells at every Pariſh Church, yet ſo <hi>wiſe,</hi> ſo <hi>grave,</hi> ſo <hi>juſt</hi> was that High Court of <hi>Parliament</hi> (to their everlaſting <hi>honour</hi> be it remembred) that no <hi>threatnings,</hi> nor <hi>feares,</hi> no <hi>promiſes</hi> nor <hi>hopes,</hi> no <hi>fierceneſſe,</hi> nor cunningly deviſed <hi>ſuggeſtion</hi> could move them to decerne a warre, or grant any Subſidie for a warre againſt us, but rather
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173870:3"/>by their <hi>ſpeeches, complaints</hi> and <hi>grievances</hi> parallel to ours, did juſtifie the Cauſe (ſo much as in them was) which we defend. This rich and recent <hi>favour</hi> doth ſo binde our hearts, that were our <hi>power</hi> never ſo great, we ſhould judge our ſelves the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthieſt of all men, and could look for no leſſe then <hi>vengeance</hi> from the <hi>righteous God,</hi> if we ſhould move <hi>hand</hi> or <hi>foot</hi> againſt that Nation ſo comfortably to us repreſented in that <hi>honourable meeting.</hi> In this our <hi>thankefull acknowledgement,</hi> we deſire that the City of <hi>London</hi> may have their own large ſhare as they well deſerve by the noble profeſſion they have given of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant affection to Religion, and the <hi>peace</hi> of both Kingdomes, notwithſtanding the continuall aſſaults of the miſleaders of the King againſt them, alwayes rendering them <hi>ſediticus</hi> in his eares. And if this which doth ſo convince us ſhall not be <hi>thought ſufficient</hi> to <hi>ſatisfie</hi> all the good people of <hi>England,</hi> We now before <hi>God</hi> and the World make offer in generall, and we make offer to ſo many of them as ſhall require it in particular, of the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> and moſt <hi>inviolable bond</hi> of our <hi>ſolemne Oath</hi> and <hi>religious atteſtation of the Great Name of GOD, who is our feare and dread, and from whom we hope for a bleſſing upon our expedition, that we intend no enmity or rapine, and shall take no mans goods, nor ingage our ſelves in blood by fighting, unleſſe we be forced unto it,</hi> which we may look for from the Papiſts and Prelats, But if any ſuch thing ſhall come from <hi>godly men,</hi> or good Partons, who love the <hi>truth of Religion,</hi> or the Kings <hi>honour</hi> and their own <hi>liberty,</hi> both the rule of <hi>Charity</hi> (which entertaineth no ſuſpicion, where there is no evill deſerving) and the ſoule of <hi>wiſdome</hi> (which teacheth that both Nations muſt now <hi>ſtand</hi> or <hi>fall</hi> together) doe forbid us to apprehend. All the deſigne of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes is for the <hi>truth of Religion,</hi> and for the <hi>juſt liberty</hi> of the Subject, and all the deviſes and doings of the enemy are for the oppreſſing of both, that our Religion may be turned into Superſtition and Atheiſme, and our <hi>liberty</hi> into baſe <hi>ſervitude</hi> and <hi>bondage.</hi> To bring this to paſſe they have certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that the blocking up of this Kingdome by Sea and Land would prove a powerfull and infallible means, For, for either within a very ſhort time ſhall we through want of <hi>trade,</hi> and ſpoyling of our goods be brought to ſuch extreame <hi>poverty</hi> and <hi>confuſion,</hi> that we ſhall miſerably deſire the <hi>conditions</hi> which we now deſpiſe, and decline, and be forced to imbrace their <hi>will</hi> for a Law, both in Church and policie, which will be a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent for the like miſery in <hi>England,</hi> who timouſly foreſeeing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173870:4"/>it may be taught by their and our danger to be more <hi>wiſe,</hi> or upon the other part, we ſhall by this Invaſion be conſtrained furiouſly and without <hi>order</hi> to break into <hi>England,</hi> which we beleeve is the moſt earneſt deſire of our common <hi>enemies,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a more ſpeedy execution of their <hi>deſigne:</hi> for we doubt not but upon our comming clamours will be raiſed, Poſts ſent, and Proclamations made, through the Kingdome, to ſlander our <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>juſt intentions</hi> (as if this had been our meaning from the beginning) to ſtirre up all the Engliſh againſt us, that once being entred in blood, they may with their own Swords extirpate their own Religion, lay a preſent <hi>foundation</hi> with their own hands for building of <hi>Rome</hi> in the midſt of them, and be made the Actors of their own and our <hi>ſlavery</hi> to continue for Ever. But in this admirable <hi>opportunity</hi> of <hi>vindication</hi> of <hi>true Religion</hi> and <hi>juſt liberty,</hi> if <hi>divine providence</hi> be looked upon with a <hi>reverend eye,</hi> and <hi>men fearing God,</hi> and loving the Kings <hi>honour,</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> of both Kingdomes, ſhall walke worthy of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, although the enemies have obtayned ſo much of their deſires, as by cords of their own twiſting, to draw us into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> yet may their maine deſigne be diſappointed, the Rope which they have made brought upon their own necks, and their wiſdome turned to <hi>foolishneſſe,</hi> which we have reaſon to hope for from that ſupreme <hi>wiſdome</hi> and <hi>power</hi> which hath in all the proceedings of this worke turned their deviſes upon their own pates that plotted them.</p>
            <p>In our <hi>Informations, Remonſtrances,</hi> and the true repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our proceedings ſince the laſt <hi>pacification,</hi> we have ſo farre expreſſed the wrongs which we have ſuſtained, and the diſtreſſes which we ſuffer, as may make manifeſt our preſſing neceſſity to take ſome other courſe for our preſent reliefe, then ſuch <hi>petitions ſupplications</hi> and <hi>commiſſions,</hi> as we have uſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with leſſe ſucceſſe then could be expected of a Kingdome from their native King. Before we ſtirred ſo much as with a <hi>petition,</hi> we indured for many yeares not onely the continuall oppoſition of the <hi>truth,</hi> and power of Religion by Prelates and Papiſts, but alſo the violation of all our <hi>liberties,</hi> and almoſt the totall ſubverſion of our Religion, which was our comfort in the ſight of <hi>God,</hi> and the glory of this Nation in the ſight of other Churches, who by the teſtimony of their Divines made our Reformation the meaſure of their wiſhes, and would have redeemed it with their greateſt worldly loſſes, when groſſe Popery was notoriouſly obtruded upon us in the Booke of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:173870:4"/>Canons and common Prayer, without conſent or knowledge of the Churches; and the plot of the Prelats and Papiſts whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered how to ſettle it in both Nations: We added to our former ſuffrings no other Armes but Prayers and <hi>teares</hi> unto <hi>God;</hi> and Petitions to our King, which were utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected; the Books and corruptions againſt which we <hi>petitioned</hi> highly exalted, and by the inſolent adviſe of thoſe who govern now his Counſells, labour to eſtabliſh their own ill acquired greatneſſe upon our oppreſſion, and the ruines of our Religion and Liberties. We were forbidden to inſiſt, under the pain of high Treaſon, when we found our ſelves thus oppoſed and born down; ſtill inſiſting in our humble deſires we ſolemnly renewed our ſolemn and Nationall Oath and Covenant for preſerving of our Religion and Liberties, and of his Majeſties Authority, knowing the violation of that Oath to be the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe which had procured our woes, and that our Repentance and turning to <hi>God</hi> were the meanes by his bleſſing for a good ſucceſſe: when contrary to our deſerving and expectation his Majeſtie was moved by wicked Counſell to march toward us with an Army, we chooſed rather to neglect ſuch courſes as might ſerve for our humane ſafety, then to fall in ſeeming diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to our King, or to give the ſmalleſt diſtaſt to our Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> and therfore disbanded our Forces, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered all holds which were craved in teſtimony of our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſo farre complyed with his Majeſties pleaſure, that notwithſtanding the determination of our lawfull former Aſſembly, called by his Majeſty, we were contented that a new free Aſſembly and Parliament ſhould be appointed, where all things both concerning our Religion and Liberties might againe be conſidered and eſtabliſhed. When matters Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall were determined in the Aſſembly according to the Conſtitutions of the Church in the preſence, and with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his Majeſties Commiſſioner, and the Parliament was conveened for perfecting the warre, although we walked ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſo warily that no juſt provocation was given to his Majeſty, yet contrary to the Laws and Cuſtomes of this Kingdome, the Parliament ſo certainly promiſed, when his Majeſty was free of thoſe bad Counſellours, was (being againe in their power) by their adviſe proroged, which to ſhew our invinſible <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> we were content to ſuffer, and did ſend up our Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners to <hi>London</hi> to render the reaſons of our demands. When our Commiſſioners and Petitions of the Parliament, called by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173870:5"/>his Majeſty, were ſo farre rejected, that they were never ſeen or heard. We ſend up our Commiſſioners againe with our <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,</hi> which contayned nothing but what was neceſſary for the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>good</hi> of the Kingdome, and was granted to us before under his Majeſties hand, yet could they find no anſwer at all which will be wondred at, and hardly beleeved by ſo many as are ſtrangers at Court, and know not the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Leivtenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the Aſſiſtance of the too too powerfull Faction of the Hiſpanioliz'd Papiſts labour to ſhew their zeale for his Majeſties greatneſſe, by oppreſſing the juſt Liberties of the free Subjects, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion in all the three Kingdomes: But in place of the gracious anſwer which we expected, our Commiſſioners were reſtrained, and one of the Noble men Impriſoned, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons of ſtrangers ſet over our heads in an inſolent and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous way, exerciſing their cruelty even againſt Women and Children, our Ships and goods taken and ſunke, and the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſtript naked, and more inhumanely uſed at the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of abuſed Authority, by the Subjects of our own King, then by Turks and Infidels, and great Armies prepared againſt us with a terrible Commiſſion to ſubdue and deſtroy our <hi>ſelves,</hi> our Religion, Liberties, Laws and all. In this extremity for us to ſend new Commiſſioners and Petitions were againſt ſence and experience, thoſe that governe the Kings Counſells being farre from any inclination or intention to ſatisfie the juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and grievances of the Subjects, as they have made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by breaking up of the Parliament in both Kingdomes, (though we know them to be often countervoted by many of that Honourable Board, more candid and peaceably minded.) To ſit ſtill in ſenſeleſneſſe and ſecurity, wayting for our own deſtruction at the diſcretion of our mercileſſe enemies (which were it not at this time with the cauſe of <hi>God</hi> would move us the leſſe) is not only againſt Religion but Nature, teaching and commanding us to ſtudy our owne <hi>preſervation.</hi> To indure continuall <hi>threatnings,</hi> and ſo great <hi>hoſtility</hi> and <hi>invaſion</hi> from yeare to yeare, which is the profeſſed policie of our enemies is impoſſible, and when we have examined our own ſtrength, more then we are able to beare: We have therfore after much agitation and debating with and amongſt our ſelves; reſolved to have our procedings, which have been canvaſed by ſo many, and are brought to ſome point of <hi>determination</hi> in our own Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to be better known to the Kings Majeſty, and the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:173870:5"/>world, and eſpecially to the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> that againſt all falſe and artificiall relations, they beeing nakedly ſeen to be what they are, we may obtaine a better grounded and more durable <hi>peace</hi> for the injoying of our own Religion, and Laws; and as we deſire the unworthy Authors of our troubles, who have come out from our ſelves to be tryed at home, and <hi>juſtice</hi> to be done upon them according to our own Laws, ſo ſhall we preſſe no further proceſſe againſt <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe pernicious Counſellours in <hi>England</hi> the Authors of all the miſeries of both Kingdomes; then what their own Parliament ſhall diſcerne to be their juſt deſerving. When we looke upon this worke of <hi>reformation</hi> from the beginning, and perceive the impreſſions of the Providence of <hi>God</hi> in it, we are forced in the midſt of all our <hi>difficulties</hi> and <hi>diſtreſſes</hi> to bleſſe <hi>God</hi> for his Fatherly care and free love to his Church and Kingdome, and to take courage and ſpirit to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>perſeverance</hi> whither he ſhall goe before us, and lead us on. When the Prelats were grown by their Rents and Lordly dignities by their power over all ſorts of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Subjects, Miniſters and others, by their places in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, Councell, Colledge of Juſtice, Exchequer and High Commiſſion, to an abſolute Dominion and greatneſſe, and ſetting the one foot upon the Church, and the other upon the State, were become miſerably inſolent, even then did the worke begin, and this was the <hi>Lords opportunity.</hi> The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings were ſmall, and promiſed no great thing, but have been ſo ſeconded and continually followed by <hi>divine providence,</hi> preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing us from ſtep to ſtep, that the neceſſity was invincible and could not be reſiſted. It cannot be expreſſed what motions filled the heart, what <hi>teares</hi> were powred forth from the <hi>eyes,</hi> and what <hi>cryes</hi> came from the <hi>mouthes</hi> of many thouſands in this Land at that time, from the ſence of the Law and power of <hi>God,</hi> rayſing them as from the <hi>dead,</hi> and giving them hopes after ſo great a deluge and vaſtation to ſee a new world, wherin Religion and Righteouſneſſe ſhould dwell. When we were many times at a pauſe, and knew not well what to doe, the <hi>feares,</hi> the <hi>furies,</hi> the <hi>peevishneſse</hi> and the plots of our demen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat adverſaries opened a way unto us, and taught us how to proceed, and what they deviſed to ruine us ſerved moſt againſt themſelves, and for rayſing and promoting the worke. <hi>O pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to be adored!</hi> Although neither Counſell nor Seſſion, nor any other Judicature hath been all this time ſitting, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173870:6"/>there have been meetings of many thouſands at ſometimes, yet have they been kept without <hi>tumult</hi> or <hi>trouble,</hi> and without exceſſe or ryot in better order and greater quietnes, then in the moſt <hi>peaceable times</hi> have been found in this Land. When we were content at the <hi>pacification</hi> to lay down Arms, and with great loſſe to live at home in <hi>pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> our wicked enemies have been like the troubled Sea when it cannot reſt, whoſe <hi>waters caſt up mire and dirt,</hi> and will have us to doe that which it ſeems the <hi>Lord</hi> hath decreed againſt them. The purity of our <hi>intentions</hi> farre from baſe and earthly reſpects, the bent and inclination of our <hi>hearts</hi> in the midſt of many dangers, the fitting of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not onely with a deſire and diſpoſition, but with ſpirit and abilities to overcome <hi>oppoſition,</hi> and the conſtant peace of <hi>heart</hi> accompanying us in our wayes, which beareth us out againſt all accuſations and aſperſions, are to us ſtrong grounds of aſſurance that <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>accepted</hi> our <hi>worke,</hi> and will not leave us: we know the <hi>Lord</hi> may uſe even wicked men in his <hi>ſervice,</hi> and may fill their ſailes with a faire gale of <hi>abilities,</hi> and carry them on with a ſtrong hand, which ſhould make us to ſearch our hearts more narrowly. But as this ought not to diſcourage his own <hi>faithfull ſervants,</hi> who out of <hi>love</hi> to his Name intend his <hi>honour,</hi> walke in his <hi>wayes,</hi> find his <hi>peace comforting them,</hi> his <hi>providence directing them,</hi> and his <hi>preſence bleſſing them</hi> in their <hi>affaires.</hi> So can it not be any juſt ground of quarrelling againſt the worke of <hi>God.</hi> Yet all theſe our incouragements which have upholden our <hi>hearts</hi> in the midſt of many <hi>troubles,</hi> could not make our entry into <hi>England</hi> warrantable, if our <hi>peace</hi> (which we earneſtly ſeek and follow after) could be found at home or elſewhere. Where it is to be found we muſt ſeeke after it, and no ſooner ſhall we finde it clearly ſecured to us, but by laying down our Armes, and by the evidences of our peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſpoſition, we ſhall make manifeſt to the world, and eſpecially to the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> that we are ſeeking nothing els but <hi>peace,</hi> and that our taking up of Armes was not for Invaſion but for Defence. No man needeth to plead by <hi>poſitive law</hi> for <hi>neceſſity.</hi> It is written in every mans <hi>heart</hi> by <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and in all actions we find men have received it by <hi>practiſe, that neceſſity is a ſoveraignity.</hi> A Law above all Laws is ſubject to no Law, and therfore is ſaid to have no Law. Where <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity commandeth,</hi> the Laws of <hi>nature</hi> and Nations give their <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> and all <hi>poſitive laws</hi> are <hi>ſilent</hi> and give place. This Law hath place, ſomtimes to <hi>excuſe,</hi> ſomtimes to <hi>extenuate,</hi> and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:173870:6"/>to <hi>juſtifie</hi> and <hi>warrant actions</hi> otherwiſe queſtionable: and no <hi>greater neceſſity</hi> can be then the <hi>preſervation of Religion,</hi> which is the <hi>ſoule</hi> of the <hi>Countrey,</hi> which is the <hi>body</hi> of our <hi>lives;</hi> who are the <hi>members,</hi> and of the <hi>honour</hi> of our King who is the <hi>head.</hi> All theſe at this rime are in a common hazard, and to <hi>preſerve</hi> and <hi>ſecure</hi> all, we know no other way under the Sunne (And if any be ſo wiſe as to know it, we deſire to heare it, and ſhall be ready to follow it) but to take order with our comon ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies where they may be found, and to ſeek our aſſurance where it may be given. The queſtion is not whether we ſhall content our ſelves with our own <hi>poverty,</hi> or <hi>enrich</hi> our ſelves in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> that queſtion is impious and abſurd. Neither is the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether we ſhall <hi>defend</hi> our ſelves at <hi>home,</hi> or <hi>invade</hi> our <hi>neighbours</hi> and deareſt Brethren? this alſo were unchriſtian and unreaſonable. But this is the queſtion, whether it be <hi>wiſdome</hi> and <hi>piety</hi> to keep our ſelves within the borders till our <hi>throats</hi> be cut, and our Religion, Laws and Countrey <hi>deſtroyed?</hi> Or, ſhall we beſtirre our ſelves, and ſeek our <hi>ſafeguard, peace</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> whether we ſhall <hi>doe</hi> or <hi>dye,</hi> whether we ſhall <hi>goe</hi> and <hi>live,</hi> or <hi>abide</hi> and <hi>perish?</hi> Or more largely to expreſſe all, Whether we who are not a few <hi>private perſons,</hi> but a whole Kingdome, ſhall lye under the burthen of ſo many <hi>accuſations,</hi> as ſcarcely in the worſt times have been charged againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, receive the Service Book, and the whole body of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, imbrace the Prelates and their abjured Hierarchy, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce our ſolemn Oath and Covenant, ſo many times ſworn by us, looſe all our labour and paines in this Cauſe, and forget our former ſlavery and wonted deſires of redemption at the deareſt rate, tickle the minds of our enemies with joy, and ſtrengthen their hands with violence, and fill the hearts of our friends with <hi>ſorrow,</hi> and their faces with <hi>shame</hi> becauſe of us; <hi>deſert</hi> and <hi>dishonour</hi> the Sonne of <hi>God</hi> whoſe Cauſe we have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, whoſe <hi>banner</hi> we heve <hi>diſplayed,</hi> and whoſe <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>power</hi> hath been this time paſt more comfortable to us, then all the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>proſperity</hi> of the world could have rendered, and draw upon our ſelves all the <hi>judgements</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath executed upon Apoſtates ſince the beginning, and ſhall we fold our hands and wayte for the perfect ſlavery of our ſelves and our Poſterity, in our <hi>ſoules, bodies,</hi> and <hi>eſtates,</hi> and (which is all one) fooliſhly to ſtand to our <hi>defence</hi> where we know it is impoſſible? Or ſha1l we ſeek our relief in following the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>God</hi> (for our <hi>neceſſity</hi> can be interpreted no leſſe) and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173870:7"/>entring by the doore which his <hi>providence</hi> hath opened unto us, when all wayes are ſtopped beſide. Our enemies at firſt did ſhroude themſelves ſo farre under the Kings Authority, that they behooved to ſtand or fall together, and that to Cenſure them was Treaſon againſt the King. Now we have ſhewen that a Kings Crown is not tyed to a Prelats Mitre, and that the one may be caſt unto the ground, and the other have a greater luſtre and glory then before. Now they take them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to another ſtarting hole, and would have men to thinke that to come into <hi>England</hi> againſt them is to come againſt <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and to purſue them although Legally is to invade the Kingdome where they live, as if the the cutting away of an Excreſcence, or the curing of an Impoſthume were the killing of the body. Let them ſecure themſelves under the ſhelter of their own <hi>phantaſies,</hi> but we are not ſo undiſſerning as like mad men to run furiouſly upon ſuch as we firſt meet with and come in our way: for although it cannot be denyed but the wrongs done to us, as the breaking of the late <hi>peace,</hi> crying us down as Rebells and Traytors, the takeing of our Ships and goods, the Impriſoning of our Commiſſioners; the Acts of Hoſtility done by the Engliſh in our Caſtles: had they been done by the State or Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> there might have been juſt cauſes of a Nationall quarrelling, yet ſeeing the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> conveend id Parliament have refuſed to contribute any ſupply againſt us, have ſhewen themſelves to be preſt with <hi>grietances</hi> like unto ours, and have earneſtly pleaded for redreſſe and remedy, and a Declaration, made that his Majeſty out of Parliament will redreſſe them, which might be a cure for the grievances of particular Subjects: but Nationall grievances require the hand of the Parliament for their cure, for prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wherof the Parliament was broken up and diſſolved. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we quarrell with the Kingdome for the injuries which we ſuſtaine, but our quarrell is onely with particular men, the enemies of both Nations: nor can they quarrell with us, for taking order with the prevalent Faction of Papiſts and Prelats the Authors of ſo many woes to both Nations.</p>
            <p>Let all who love Religion and their <hi>liberty</hi> joyne againſt the common enemies, and let them be accurſed that ſhall not ſeek the preſervation of their neighbour Nation, both in Religion and Laws, as their own, as knowing that the ruine of one will prove the ruine both. And knowing well (as having from their own Councels diſcovered it) that the ruine of both was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173870:7"/>intended, and that it was ever their plot and purpoſe, that if they could not ingage our deareſt Brethren, and neighbour Nation in a Warre for our <hi>deſtruction;</hi> then to give us ſome ill aſſured <hi>peace,</hi> which might bind our hands and hold us quiet, untill the yoake of bondage were more heavily and unremove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably layd upon our Brethren of <hi>England</hi> by the help of ſuch an Army as was pretended to be gathered againſt us, rooting out the Godly people and active ſpirits of that Nation and all thoſe who as good Patriots ſtand well affected to Religion, and their juſt <hi>liberties,</hi> and might be ſuſpected would dare ſtirre for the defence and maintenance of either, and there after eaſily find ground to break againe with us, when they were once aſſured that we were like to ſtand alone: And all the benefit or our <hi>peace</hi> ſhould be to be laſt <hi>deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as we atteſt the <hi>God</hi> of heaven that thoſe and no other are our <hi>intentions,</hi> ſo upon the ſame greateſt atteſtation doe we declare that for atchieving thoſe ends, we ſhall neither ſpare our <hi>paines, fortunes,</hi> nor <hi>lives</hi> which we know cannot be more profitably and honourably ſpent. That we ſhall not take from our Friends and Brethren from a <hi>thread</hi> even to a <hi>shooe latchet</hi> but for our own moneys, and the juſt payment: That we come amongſt them as their Friends and Brethren, very ſenſible of their by-paſt ſuffrings and preſent dangers both in Religion and Liberties, and moſt willing to doe them all the good we can, like as we certainly expect that they (from the like ſence of our hard condition and intollerable diſtreſſe which hath forced us to come from our own Countrey) will joyne and concurre with us in the moſt juſt and Noble wayes for obtayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their and our moſt juſt deſires. And when our own <hi>moneys</hi> and meanes are ſpent, we ſhall crave nothing but upon ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſurety of payment how ſoon poſſibly it can be made, what is neceſſary for the entertaynment of our Army, which we are aſſured ſo many as love Religion and the <hi>peace</hi> of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes will willingly offer, as that which they know we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not want, and in their wiſe foreſight will provide the way to furniſh neceſſaries, and to receive the <hi>ſurety.</hi> This courſe being kept by both ſides, will neither harme our Brethren (for they ſhall be ſatisfied to the laſt <hi>farthing</hi>) nor our ſelves, who look for a recompenſe from the <hi>rich providence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> for whoſe ſake we have hazarded the loſſe of all things.</p>
            <p>The eſcapes of ſome Souldiers (if any ſhall happen) we truſt ſhall not be imputed to us, who ſhall labour by all meanes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173870:8"/>prevent them more carefully, and puniſh them more ſeverely then if done to our ſelves, and in our own Countrey. Our profeſſed enemies the Papiſts, Prelats, with their adherents, and the receivers of their goods and geir, we conceive will be more provident then to refuſe us neceſſary <hi>ſuſtentation,</hi> when they remember what Councell was given by them for decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all our poſſeſſions to be <hi>forfeited</hi> and to be diſpoſed of to them as well deſerving Subjects.</p>
            <p>We ſhall demand nothing of the Kings Majecty but the ſettling and ſecureing of the <hi>true Religion</hi> and <hi>liberties</hi> of this Kingdome according to the Conſtitutions and Acts of the late Aſſemblies and Parliament, and what a juſt Prince oweth by the Laws of <hi>God</hi> and the Countrey to his grieved Subjects, coming before him with their humble <hi>deſires</hi> and <hi>ſupplications.</hi> Our abode in <hi>England</hi> ſhall be no longer time then in their Parliament, our juſt <hi>grievances</hi> and <hi>complaints</hi> may be heard and redreſſed, ſufficient aſſurance given for the legall tryall and <hi>punishment</hi> of the Authors of their and our evills; and for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming and injoying their and our Religion and Liberties in <hi>peace,</hi> againſt the machynations of Romiſh contrivance acted by their degenerate Countrey-men. Our returning thereafter ſhall be with expedition in a peaceable and orderly way farre from all moleſtation, and we truſt the effect ſhall be againſt Papiſts, the extirpation of Popery, againſt Prelats, the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Church, againſt Atheiſts, the flouriſhing of the Goſpell, and againſt Traytours and Firebrands; a perfect and dureable <hi>union</hi> and <hi>love</hi> between the two Kingdomes, which he grant who knoweth our intentions and deſires, and is able to bring them to paſſe. And if any more be required, <hi>God</hi> will reveale it and goe before both Nations, and if <hi>God</hi> goe before us who will not follow, or refuſe to put their <hi>necks to the worke of the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
